All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We are a דף daf behind.
Today's official דף daf is נ"ו. Nun Vav. We pick up on
נ"ה Nun Hey with איתמר. Itmar. We have just listed in the
משנה Mishna the basic idea of 200 and 100
and the issue that the כתובה Ketubah kicks in from אירוסין. Erusin.
I should mention that a thing that's not explicit here because our
משנה Mishna talks about if a כתובה Ketubah was written whether the
תוספת Tosefet begins from the time of אירוסין Erusin or נישואין, Nissu'in,
which is what if a כתובה Ketubah is not written, does the
200 and 100 already begin at the time of אירוסין Erusin or
not? That's not explicit, although the sense one gets from the previous
סוגיא Sugya and other סוגיות Sugyot is that those do begin even
if a כתובה Ketubah is not written. But our משנה Mishna addresses
itself to a written כתובה Ketubah with a תוספת Tosefet and whether
that begins the whether the תוספת Tosefet begins from אירוסין Erusin or
from נישואין. Nissu'in.
And then other issues that we've seen before about whether you could
make it less than 200 and 100. The גמרא Gemara addresses itself
to the idea that when there is a תוספת Tosefet it gets
the status of the כתובה Ketubah itself and you have a whole
nice long list of areas in which it matters whether something is
just an independent obligation in a שטר Shtar or whether it's specifically
a כתובה Ketubah obligation. And now we pick up with the following
which is actually going to be a very sort of a terse
list of debates of two schools in a whole row of cases.
Let's take a look, most of which having to do with כתובה.
Ketubah. איתמר Itmar it was taught, four lines from the top on
נ"ה עמוד א', Nun Hey Amud Aleph, כתובת בנין דכרין. Ketuvat Benin
Dichrin. This כתובה Ketubah of the male sons where the male sons
inherit their mother's כתובה, Ketubah, the dowry that she brings in, the
200 and the 100 and so on, in order if there are
other competing heirs they get specifically their mother's כתובה Ketubah if their
mother predeceased their father.
So in terms of that, פומבדיתא Pumbedita אמרי Amrei לא טרפי ממשעבדי,
Lo Trefi Mimshabedi, that they do not those sons do not take
it out from cannot collect it from land that has a lien
on it. So their mother brought in $10,000 in her dowry and
there is not now
and when the father dies none of that property is in the
estate itself or there's no property in the estate itself, but the
father sold a field of that value to other people. Is it
like a debt and there's a lien
on the field and they can collect it from third parties or
not? So פומבדיתא Pumbedita says no they cannot collect, ירתין תנן. Yarsun
Tenan. The language in the כתובה Ketubah is they will inherit. So
it's like an inheritance, it's not like a debt and therefore they
only get what's in the estate when the father dies.
דבי מתא מחסיא Dbei Mata Chasya אמרי Amrei טרפי ממשעבדי, Tarfi Mimshabedi,
no they can collect it from things that have liens.
יסבון תנן. Yispun Tenan. It says they will take, means that it's
treated as a debt. So is this treated as a debt as
a lien on the estate or is this treated
as an inheritance? And this was an issue we had before as
well about whether it's seen as an inheritance or a debt where
before it sort of had both statuses. Anyway, here the גמרא Gemara
says והלכתא לא טרפי ממשעבדי ירתין תנן. Vehilchata Lo Tarfi Mimshabedi Yarsun
Tenan.
We rule that we treat it as an inheritance, at least for
these הלכות Halachot for most הלכות, Halachot, and therefore they can only
collect it from property that is in the estate not property that
was sold in the father's life.
If it had a lien on it, that would mean that it
would be a debt would be collectible against the father, right? If
the father didn't pay back so somebody would be able to come
and take that some third party?
That's always true that if the father borrowed money and somebody has
a lien that they can collect that from the estate and they
can collect it from places where the father sold. This is different.
This is that the
is it seen like the sons have a lien against their father's
estate? Meaning there's no third party. The sons are entitled to the
$10,000 that their mother brought in in the dowry. Is that a
lien that they have on their father's estate? So if the father
sold property in their life they can then go ahead and collect
it from that or is it just that they inherit if it's
in the estate when the father dies?
In other words did the father incur a debt to the sons
or not?
Exactly. Is the sons' right for the כתובה Ketubah of their mother,
is that a debt that's against the father's estate?
Mother's predeceased
the father, yeah.
Was there a different גרסא? Girsah? I mean because I'm just looking
at the משנה Mishna in נ"ב עמוד ב', Nun Bet Amud Bet,
it says at least yeah that's the question what are the...
right
so that's the question what is the גרסא Girsah of the משנה?
Mishna? That's the question of ירתין, Yarsun, יסבון Yisbun yeah so if
I wasn't clear the question of ירתין Yarsun or יסבון Yisbun is
a question of either what was the גרסא Girsah in the משנה
Mishna which is what it sounds like in the גמרא Gemara where
it says תנן Tenan or what was the standard נוסח כתובה Nusach
Ketubah okay because there could have been obviously competing נוסח כתובות Nusach
Ketubot around. Okay, מטלטלי. Metalteli. Now another issue. מטלטלי ואיתנהו בעינייהו ולא
שוות. Metalteli V'isnhu B'einaihu V'lo Shvat.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, all right.
Oh, that's good. Okay. Wow, that's really. Okay. מטלטלי metaltlei now, let's
say there is chattel and it's בעיניהו. be'einaihu. Now, בלא שבועה. belo
shvuah.
Now, the, now here's the point that a widow can collect her
כתובה ketubah from the estate of the orphans and she has to
collect it so normally we say with a שבועה. shvuah. Why does
she have to make a שבועה? shvuah? She has to make a
שבועה shvuah because it's possible that the husband before he died set
aside some property, some chattel, you know, and basically said here, this
will be your כתובה, ketubah, I don't want you have to have
to deal with the heirs, just go ahead and collect your כתובה
ketubah from, I don't know, from the china here and set aside
some Wedgwood china or whatever for her כתובה. ketubah. So she has
to take a שבועה shvuah when she comes to collect her כתובה
ketubah from the heirs that her כתובה ketubah has not been paid
up because maybe the husband before he died prepaid the כתובה ketubah
or gave her chattel that would be sort of designated for collecting
her כתובה. ketubah. So let's say she's actually coming to collect the
כתובה ketubah from
chattel. Okay? So מטלטלי דאיתנהו בעיניהו metaltlei d'itnehu be'einaihu now actually and
what it is is that the husband says before he dies, he
says and we have witnesses and he says I want you to
collect your כתובה ketubah from this Wedgwood china. Okay, so that's מטלטלי
דאיתנהו בעיניהו. metaltlei d'itnehu be'einaihu. So בלא שבועה, belo shvuah, that she
can collect without a שבועה. shvuah. The whole reason she normally needs
a שבועה shvuah is because maybe he did exactly this, maybe already
designated some chattel. So if we know that he designated chattel, so
we don't have to be worried that he designated other things for
this. This is what he designated for it, so there's no need
to make a שבועה shvuah that it might have already been paid
up.
בלא שבועה. belo shvuah. ליתנהו בעיניהו. leitnehu be'einaihu. Now let's say the
Wedgwood china got broken or whatever. Okay, so now she has to
collect it from the estate, but we know that the husband already
had designated this. So presumably that should eliminate, so it's like a
little hybrid. On the one hand she's collecting from the קרקע karka
where she normally needs a שבועה. shvuah. On the other hand, we
know he had designated specific מטלטלין metaltelin for the כתובה, ketubah, so
there's really not much of a concern that he might have designated
other מטלטלין, metaltelin, so there's really no concern that he might have
already had her כתובה ketubah paid up. So maybe she shouldn't need
a שבועה. shvuah. So what do we say? So ליתנהו בעיניהו, leitnehu
be'einaihu, פומבדיתא אמרי בלא שבועה. Pumbedita amri belo shvuah. She can collect
again without a שבועה. shvuah. We know that there was no other
מטלטלי, metaltlei, I mean we can reasonably assume there was no other
מטלטלי metaltlei he would have pre-designated.
So therefore, why should she need a שבועה shvuah now to collect
from the קרקע? karka? But מתא מחסיא אמרי בשבועה. Mata Mechasya amri
b'shvuah.
But those of מתא מחסיא Mata Mechasya say she collects again with
a שבועה shvuah now that she's coming to collect from קרקע, karka,
that's the general rule that when you collect from קרקע karka you
make a שבועה. shvuah. והלכתא בלא שבועה. ve'hilchata belo shvuah. And the
הלכה halacha is without a שבועה. shvuah. We don't do a type
of לא פלוג. lo plug. We say the reason that the widow
makes a שבועה shvuah when she comes to collect the כתובה ketubah
is in case there was been מטלטלין metaltelin that has been designated,
and here we know there was מטלטלין metaltelin that was designated and
it wasn't used because it all got broken or something. But we're
not concerned that there might be other מטלטלין metaltelin and therefore there's
no need to make a שבועה. shvuah.
In general, what's the שבועה shvuah that someone would take?
That she did not already get her כתובה ketubah paid up.
A woman comes to collect her כתובה. ketubah.
This is not a normal, well, normally a person comes with a
שטר, shtar, they just collect, they don't need a שבועה, shvuah, they
have a שטר. shtar. But here the husband and wife have been
married together for twenty years, so we're concerned that maybe the שטר
shtar in some way, maybe he had already given her some property
to collect from, some מטלטלין. metaltelin. Some קרקע karka we would know
because we know what his קרקע karka is. She would have the
title. But מטלטלין metaltelin she could have just her pocketed it or
something. No, he's not paying it up, he's designating it and saying,
I don't want you have to deal with my kids after I
die.
Here, here, you know, this will be designated for you and then
after I die, just go ahead and just take that and just.
But if he said I paid it up while I was alive,
he would not be believed.
I'm not going to deal with all the possibilities. The basic point
right now is that she normally makes a שבועה shvuah that he
had not pre-designated מטלטלין metaltelin or pre-paid up the כתובה ketubah for
her. And now that we know that he had designated מטלטלין, metaltelin,
maybe there's no need for a שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
ייחד לה ארעא בארבע מצרהא. yiched lah ar'ah b'arba mitzreha. Let's say
a similar way in which we have no concern
that the כתובה ketubah was already paid up, like he's designated and
says here this land with the four, and he gave the four
directions of the land, all of the, you know, the exact sort
of parameters, borders. Right. So there's no question that the כתובה ketubah
was paid up with something else, this because he said I want
you to collect from this land. So we shouldn't have to make
her make a שבועה shvuah that she didn't get it paid up
already because he designated what the land would be that she would
collect from. So in that case, בלא שבועה, belo shvuah, she can
collect without a שבועה. shvuah. בחד מצרא, b'chad mitzra, if let's say
he only designated the land with giving one border, not the four
borders. So he really hasn't designated the land, we don't know how
much land he's setting aside for her. So maybe that's like nothing
was designated, and maybe again we have to be concerned that he
gave her, prepaid the כתובה ketubah or, you know, set aside מטלטלין
metaltelin for the כתובה, ketubah, and maybe she should have to make
a שבועה. shvuah. Because maybe this wasn't. And under real designating. So
in this case, פומבדיתא אמרי בלא שבועה, Pumbedita amrei belo shvuah, בני
מתא מחסיא אמרי בשבועה. benei mata mechasaya amrei bishvuah. פומבדיתא Pumbedita says
collect without a שבועה shvuah and בני מתא מחסיא benei mata mechasaya
says you make a שבועה, shvuah, והלכתא בלא שבועה, vehilchasa belo shvuah,
and again we say without a שבועה shvuah we're going lenient on
her. Okay, so I can't, it's very funny, the גמרא Gemara does
not really spell out what's behind these debates or what's behind פסקנינג
paskening one side. Anyway, so far now we've פסקנד paskened two things.
Number one is that בנין דכרין benin dichrin is like an inheritance
and therefore they don't have a lien against the estate and they
can only collect from land that's in the estate when the father
dies. And the other is that the widow who has to make
a שבועה shvuah to collect her כתובה ketubah that it hasn't been
prepaid, if however מטלטלין metaltelin has been designated, even if that מטלטלין
metaltelin is no longer בעין, be'en, or if land has been designated,
even if it hasn't been designated on all four borders, that's considered
enough of an evidence that the husband did not set aside other
property for the כתובה, ketubah, enough of an evidence that the כתובה
ketubah has not been prepaid, and therefore she can collect without a
שבועה. shvuah.
Yeah, but the תוספתא, tosefta, the reason why
it has to
be כנכסי ke-konchasai and it has to be from קרקע karka and
all
these other גמרות, Gemaras, so how are we able to move away
from that? But it's now specifically some land and it can even
be מטלטלין. metaltelin. So, that's a good question and the simple answer
is that this doesn't necessarily mean that it limits her other rights.
It's just giving her some special rights, there's a way you could
have a primary זכות zechus on this קרקע, karka, on this מטלטלין
metaltelin without limiting her right to the other stuff if this stuff
isn't around. You see that because the גמרא Gemara said that if
the מטלטלין metaltelin isn't בעין, be'en, she's still going to collect from
קרקע. karka. So clearly when he designates the מטלטלין, metaltelin, it's not
to limit her ability to collect from other things, it's to give
her more rights to collect specifically from this. But that is a
good question.
And in part of משנה, mishnah, the reason why they really said
if you designate a specific piece of land and it didn't work,
that was on נ"א, nun aleph, that was because it was worth
less than the כתובה. ketubah.
Yes, exactly. Right. So Michael's asking a good question, which is that
the limiting here and saying you can collect from this land or
you can collect from this מטלטלין metaltelin is not to limit her
exclude her liens from the other thing, it's to give her special
rights to this particular thing.
And you see that because the גמרא Gemara here says that if
the מטלטלין metaltelin isn't בעין, be'en, she's still collecting. So it's not
like her rights are limited to this. And the earlier discussion is
when somebody wanted to limit the rights to something that was worth
less or only to exclude other types of things. So those are
good questions of how much can the liens be limited or can
they be either increased in one area or limited from the other
stuff and so those are good questions. But the basic let's assume
for now that what we're dealing with is that it was an
additional right,
not limiting the other right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, last one of these three debates,
אמר לעדים, amar le-edim, here having nothing to do with כתובה ketubah
issues, כתבו וחתמו והבו ליה. kisvu ve-chasmu ve-havu lei. So somebody on
his deathbed basically said to witnesses,
or might not have been on his deathbed, but anyway, somebody said,
go ahead, write over this שטר, shtar, let's say a writ on
a gift of land, write it, sign it, and give it to
him. He wanted to give land to a certain person, so he
told witnesses, write over a bill of a deed and give it
to him. So קנו מיניה, kanu minei, if they did a קנין,
kinyan, which is like a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, like the handkerchief,
לא צריך אימלוכי ביה, lo tzarich imluchei bei, they don't have to
check in with him before they give him the deed. Because that
shows he has full גמיירות דעת, gmiros da'as, he's really committed to
it, and they go ahead and do it. לא קנו מיניה, lo
kanu minei, if they didn't do a קנין, kinyan, so even though
he said this verbally, is that enough to go ahead and enact
the whole transfer not in his presence? So פומבדיתא אמרי לא צריך
אימלוכי ביה, Pumbedita amrei lo tzarich imluchei bei, they don't have to
check in with him and again בני מתא מחסיא אמרי צריך אימלוכי
ביה, benei mata mechasaya amrei tzarich imluchei bei, and those of מתא
מחסיא mata mechasaya say no, if it was just verbal and there
was no קנין, kinyan, before they actually finalize the
transfer, they need to check in with him. והלכתא צריך אימלוכי ביה,
vehilchasa tzarich imluchei bei, and the הלכה halachah is they have to
check in with him, which makes a lot of sense. Okay, so
that was an interesting list of debates about בני מתא מחסיא benei
mata mechasaya and פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, most two out of the three of
which were about כתובה. ketubah. Moving on, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer. Now back to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah who says that even though you write the
תוספתא tosefta from the time of אירוסין, erusin, the obligation doesn't kick
in until נישואין, nissuin, because the whole reason he wrote it was
with the anticipation of the נישואין. nissuin. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, איתמר, itmar, it was taught רב ורבי נתן, Rav ve-Rabbi
Natan, חד אמר הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, chad amar halachah ke-Rabbi
Elazar ben Azariah, we rule like this, וחד אמר אין הלכה כרבי
אלעזר בן עזריה, ve-chad amar ein halachah ke-Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah, we
don't rule like him. תסתיים, tistayem, let's conclude רבי נתן הוא דאמר
הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Natan hu de-amar halachah ke-Rabbi Elazar
ben Azariah, that Rabbi Natan is the one who says we rule
like him, דשמעינן ליה לרבי נתן דאזל בתר אומדנא, deshameinan lei le-Rabbi
Natan de'azal batar umdana, because we know that Rabbi Natan says דאזל
בתר אומדנא. de'azal batar umdana. He goes by אומדנא. umdana. אומדנא umdana
is an assessment of the person's intent, and we look at that
and not just what's written. Because if you just look at what's
written, the guy wrote in the שטר shtar that he's adding the
תוספתא tosefta and the שטר shtar was written before the נישואין. nissuin.
So if you go by what's directly in front of you, you
should say the obligation kicks in at the time of the אירוסין,
erusin, the obligation kicks in at the time the שטר shtar was
written. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah says no, even
though it's written... written in the document and the document was written,
you know, a year before the נישואין nisuin. *Nisuin*, we assume that
he only meant to do it at the time of the נישואין
nisuin *Nisuin*. So we try to figure out what's in his mind
and we use that to interpret the context of what's in front
of us and we go by that, you know, to shape and
to interpret something that is, you know, right there written in front
of us. So that's אזלינן בתר אומדנא azlinan batar umdana *Azlinan batar
umdana*. Okay, so דאמר d'amar רב Rav, נתן *d'amar
Rav Natan* הלכה halacha כרבי שמעון Shimon, בן שזורי במבוכן *b'mesukan*. Now
where do we see Rav Natan goes like this? 'Cause he says
we go like Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri by a person who is
endangered, about to die. What does that mean? So there's a משנה
Mishnah, *Mishnah* in גיטין *Gittin* that says that if somebody is going
out on a far away journey or he's being taken out to
be executed, and he says write a גט Get *Get* for my
wife, we assume he doesn't just mean write a גט Get *Get*
for my wife, we assume he means write a גט get *Get*
for my wife and give it to her because he is afraid
he's going to die and maybe she'll have to do יבום Yibum
*Yibum* or he might not return from the journey and there'll be
a question whether he's alive or dead. So in those contexts we
assume he means write it and give it to her. Rabbi Shimon
ben Shezuri says that even if it's even if he's a guy
like basically who's on his deathbed, okay, he's a מסוכן *Mesukan*, he's
about to die, and he says write a גט get, *Get* for
my wife, we assume he means write it and give it. So
the funny thing is that in both of those contexts we go
by אומדנא umdana. *Umdana*, right? Even the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna
Kamma* says that we that we assume that when he says write,
he means write and give. It's just Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri goes
one step further. Like the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* says
these two cases, Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri says even the third case.
It's not like they really are debating whether you go by אומדנא
umdana? *Umdana*, right? We could all say you go by אומדנא umdana,
*Umdana*. The question is, which cases do we assume...
Why wouldn't you be in a deathbed?
Yeah, I'm not clear to me because I think the idea is
that if you're going on a sea journey or you're going on
being taken out to be executed, you're a little bit pressed for
time and, you know, a person on his deathbed might know he's
dying but he doesn't assume like he's not rushed. Okay, so he's
I can take my time. Well, you know, if the if the
if the captain is saying the foghorn is blowing, not the foghorn,
whatever it is, you know, the thing is blowing and the ship
is leaving and you're running to the airport or whatever you're doing,
or they're schlepping you out to the guillotine, you might not have
the, you know, the frame of mind to say everything fully, whereas
the guy's on his deathbed, he probably means he wants to get
given to his wife, but it doesn't have that extra element of
being rushed. Okay, so that's the debate. But everybody goes agrees you
go by אומדנא umdana. *Umdana*. Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri is just willing
to take it, you know, to be a little bit more doesn't
need as much context in order to interpret it. Okay, but Rav
Natan rules like him. So that shows that Rav Natan is more
inclined to try to interpret what's in somebody's mind even if the
context is a little less obvious. Okay, so he rules like Rabbi
Shimon ben Shezuri by מסוכן *Mesukan* and ובתרומת מעשר של דמאי *u'beterumat
ma'aser shel demai*. Now תרומת מעשר של דמאי *Terumat ma'aser shel demai*
does not is not our case, but I'll just tell you what
it is. Basically was a debate that somebody took, you know, when
you buy דמאי *demai* grain from an עם הארץ *Am Ha'aretz* and
you don't know if they took מעשר *ma'aser*, you assume they took
תרומה *terumah*, you don't know if they took מעשר *ma'aser*, so you
take מעשר *ma'aser* rabbinically. And then from that מעשר *ma'aser* you take
תרומת מעשר *terumat ma'aser*. Now you took that תרומת מעשר *terumat ma'aser*
and what happened? After you took that תרומת מעשר *terumat ma'aser*, it
accidentally fell back in. Okay, so now there's no way to fix
it. When the תרומת מעשר *terumat ma'aser* falls back into the מעשר
*ma'aser*, to the main grain, there's you have to throw it all
or you have to sell it all to a כהן Kohen, *Kohen*.
There's no way you can fix it. Yeah, yeah. So Rabbi Shimon
ben Shezuri says in that case that you're really stuck and there's
no solution, you can just ask the עם הארץ *Am Ha'aretz* and
trust what the עם הארץ *Am Ha'aretz* says because otherwise רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says you'd have to throw the whole thing out, or not
throw it out but you'd have to sell it to a כהן
Kohen, *Kohen*, there's no way you could eat it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
says also the עם הארץ *Am Ha'aretz* might be afraid to lie
in terms of the because of תרומת מעשר *terumat ma'aser* is more
weighty to him than just מעשר *ma'aser*, just טבל *tevel*. So anyway,
so he says, so Rav Natan says we rule like Rabbi Shimon
ben Shezuri in that case as well and you could ask the
עם הארץ *Am Ha'aretz*. Okay, but that's not really our case. The
basic point is Rav Natan says that you rule like Rabbi Shimon
ben Shezuri by this guy who's on his deathbed, so you see
he's prepared to go by אומדנא umdana. *Umdana*. So here too, even
though the שטר Shtar, *shtar* is written before the נישואין nissuin. *nisuin*,
Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri says you'll go by אומדנא umdana *Umdana* and
you'll say that the תוספת tosefet? *tosefet* won't kick in until the
נישואין nissuin. *nisuin*. Okay, so that's what we're going to say, he's
the one that rules like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah. *Rabbi Eleazar ben Azaria*, not Rav. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ורב לא lo, אזיל בתר אומדנא umdana *Ve'Rav lo azil batar
umdana*? Are you telling me Rav doesn't go by אומדנא umdana *Umdana*
by assessing his דעת daat *da'at*? והאיתמר *Ve'ha'itmar*, it was taught: מתנת
שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv Me'ra. *Matnat Shechiv Mera*. A guy is giving
a gift on his deathbed. Deathbed bequest. שכתב בה קנין Kinyan. *Shekatav
bah kinyan*.
Now, normally a deathbed bequest has the following qualities. Number one is
you don't have to actually do a קנין Kinyan *kinyan*. דברי שכיב
מרע Shchiv Me'ra, ככתובים וכמסורים דמי *Divrei shechiv mera k'ketuvim u'k'mesurim dami*.
Just verbal deathbed bequest, the Rabbis made like a binding will, like
a binding gift, and you don't even have to write it, you
don't have to do a קנין Kinyan, *kinyan*, you don't have to
do anything. Number two, because we assume it was only intended to
be given at the guy if the guy were to die, if
he actually recovered, then it's all reversed. Now this person did a
deathbed bequest. He said here I am on my deathbed and I
am bequeathing blah blah blah, and we wrote that all into the
document. There's actually a language you write in the document. He said
כדשכיב ומוטל בערסיה
when the guy was there lying in his deathbed this is what
he said dot dot dot dot dot and then after doing that
whole sort of thing he actually did a קנין. Kinyan. Okay, and
he said and he did like he did a קנין סודר Kinyan
Sudar and he took the handkerchief as a way of saying and
to make it binding. So what's the story because what he now
has done is he's created a hybrid because a קנין Kinyan. is
what you do by a normal transaction, not by a deathbed bequest.
So מתנת שכיב מרע שכתוב בה קנין. Matnas Shchiv Me'ra Shekasuv Bah
Kinyan. דבי רב משמיה דרב אמרי, D'vei Rav Mishmeih D'rav Amri, so
in the house of רב, Rav, the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב, Rav,
they say in the name of רב, Rav ארכביה אתרי רכשי. Archevyei
Atrei Rechi. It's like he's riding on two chariots. ושמואל אמר, V'Shmuel
Amar, לא ידענא מאי אדון בה. Lo Yadana Mai Adun Bah. I
don't know what to do with it. Okay, so it's a hybrid.
So we'll, no, no, now we're going to explain what it means.
דבי רב משמיה דרב אמרי, D'vei Rav Mishmeih D'rav Amri, ארכביה אתרי
רכשי, Archevyei Atrei Rechi, he's riding on two chariots. הרי היא כמתנת
ברי Harei Hi K'Matnas Bari והרי היא כמתנת שכיב מרע. V'Harei Hi
K'Matnas Shchiv Me'ra. It has, it's both like a gift of a
well person and a gift of a person in his deathbed. הרי
היא כמתנת ברי דאם עמד אינו יכול לחזור בה. Harei Hi K'Matnas
Bari De'im Amad Eino Yachol Lachazor Bah. So on the one hand,
if he recovers, it's not reversed. So it is, meaning who, it's
better for the receiver, it has all of the power, you know,
it gives all of the rights to the receiver, both benefits. Sorry,
he said he made a קנין, Kinyan right? He made a קנין.
Kinyan, So the person who received it, number one, it, it's binding
even if the guy gets better. So in that way it's like
a מתנת ברי. Matnas Bari. And הרי היא כמתנת שכיב מרע Harei
Hi K'Matnas Shchiv Me'ra and it has the, it's to the benefit
of the receiver like a gift of a שכיב מרע, sh'chiv mera
it's a stronger gift if you want to frame it that way,
שאם אמר הלואתי לפלוני הלואתי לפלוני. She'im Amar Halva'asi LiPloni Halva'asi LiPloni.
If he wanted to transfer a debt, you know, he said, this
guy owes me a thousand dollars, I'm transferring it to שמעון, that
works. And if you're a well person and you want to transfer
a debt, then you have, it's much more complicated. You can't transfer
a debt just with a קנין סודר, Kinyan Sudar, right? A debt
is an abstract idea, entity. And what you need to transfer a
debt is a whole, is a whole debate, but you cannot do
it just by a simple קנין. Kinyan So basically what רב Rav
says is it has the power of both. Okay, it has the
strength of both. It has all the strength of a gift of
a well person, so even if he gets better it's still binding.
And it has all the, all the strength of the gift of
a person in his deathbed that it works even for a wide
range of things that normally a person can't transfer. And presumably you
would even combine both. So if he gave a loan of a
hundred thousand dollars to ראובן Reuven and he got better, it would
still be binding. Right? You understand normally you can't have both of
those coming together. Right? It's either one or the other. But this
actually has the power of both of them combined. Both of a
gift and of a loan. Both, no, not of a loan, a
gift and a מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shchiv Me'ra The loan is
that you can transfer a debt in your deathbed bequest. Normally if
I, if you owed me a hundred thousand dollars and I wanted
to transfer it to דוד, David, I couldn't just do a קנין
Kinyan or whatever. You have to do a שטר, Shtar you have
to do, it's complicated to transfer a loan. But in my deathbed
bequest I'm allowed to transfer that. I would pay him back instead.
Yeah, pay him instead. Exactly. And the other, so it has the
power of a deathbed bequest that you can transfer loans through it
and it has the power of a gift of a well person
that even if I recover it's still binding. So now I transfer
your hundred thousand dollar debt to דוד, David, I got better, דוד
David still owns it even though normally there would be no way
that could happen under normal circumstances. He still pays him back. Well,
that's not exactly clear, that's a good question. Because if you think
about a גט and a כהן, if the כהן, it says, and
he knows his, the brother doesn't want the, any יבום case, and
he says give a גט to the wife and he gets better,
then he can't. I understand, I understand. Okay, but so that's, it's
not necessarily, it very well takes place after he dies. Okay, anyway
for רב Rav. it's a case of a hybrid. Okay, so it
works with the irreversible power of a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari and
it works on the scope of things that a מתנת שכיב מרע
matnat sh'chiv mera, works and that's why you did both so that
you have the strength of both types of gifts. All right, so
that's how it works for רב. Rav, ושמואל אמר, V'Shmuel Amar, שמואל
Shmuel says לא ידענא מאי אדון בה, Lo Yadana Mai Adun Bah,
I don't know what to deal with it. שמא לא גמר להקנותו
אלא בשטר ואין שטר לאחר מיתה. Shema Lo Gamar Lehaktoso Ela BiShtar
V'Ein Shtar Le'achar Misa. שמואל Shmuel goes the opposite way, he says
maybe since you did a קנין, Kinyan a קנין kinyan you want
to work, mean that you want to make it work as a
מתנת ברי. Matnas Bari. Since you want to make it work as
a מתנת ברי, Matnas Bari, that means that you want it to,
a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari if you do a קנין kinyan you
have to write the שטר Shtar, and then hand over the שטר,
shtar and that would, and, but on the other hand, you, because
you're in your deathbed, maybe you only wanted it to work after
you died and that can't, and, and a מתנת ברי Matnas Bari
doesn't work after you died. Meaning, as opposed to רב, Rav right,
what רב Rav says is, is that it is, is that it
works with the power of both. What שמואל Shmuel says is you've
basically undermined yourself. How have you undermined yourself? Because he says the
fact that you're in your, on your deathbed means that you want
it to work only after you died, right, that's what a deathbed
bequest is. But the fact that you've done it with a קנין
shows you want it to work like a normal transfer. And a
normal transfer, if I wanted to make something, if I wanted to
transfer something after I died, okay, and then that wouldn't work, I
have to transfer something while I'm alive. Once after I'm dead it's
not my property anymore to transfer. Okay. So therefore שמואל Shmuel basically
says nothing works. רב Rav says everything works to the max, and
שמואל Shmuel basically says nothing works. Is that pretty clear guys? I
mean, I know this isn't our סוגיה sugya yet about מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnat sh'chiv mera, but yes? So there's no loan, no transfer.
Forget the loan, any transfer doesn't work according to שמואל. Shmuel. Have
I lost everybody or people with me? Are you all with me,
more or less? Okay. The one piece I'm not holding onto is
how these cases of the מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat sh'chiv mera. etc.,
is connected back to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
It's all a question about whether you go by אומדנא. umdana. Now
what תוספות says is, is that how do you know that רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel are debating אומדנא? umdana Maybe both of them
are trying to determine אומדנא, umdana, but they have different approaches to
אומדנא.
umdana So well רש"י Rashi already gives an answer and רש"י says
because שמואל Shmuel doesn't really שמואל Shmuel
basically is saying since I don't know what to do, it's sort
of like I'm not confident enough about what he meant and basically
according to שמואל Shmuel like it's like I'm not going to change
any property, like I don't know what the nature of this weird
שטר shtar is and therefore like let's leave everything the way it
was. Like we're not going to assume any property transferred as a
result of this thing. Whereas רב Rav feels confident enough to assume
what the power of this hybrid is that he's actually going to
now transfer property as a result of it. So רב Rav is
really willing to go by his assumption of what the guy's intending.
שמואל Shmuel doesn't really know what the guy is intending and really
feels like a little bit like paralyzed and therefore we can't do
anything based on this. רב Rav says no, I'm going to tell
you he wanted this to work as like the best strength of
both a מתנת בריא matnat bari and a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas
sh'chiv mera, So it's going to work even if he gets better
and it's going to work even on a wide range of things
and רב Rav is willing to transfer property as a result. שמואל
Shmuel says maybe he wanted to do a hybrid that doesn't make
any sense. He wanted to make it work after he died, but
he wanted to make it work like a normal קנין of a
בריא bari and a normal קנין of a בריא bari doesn't work
after you die so maybe you have nothing. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says anyway what we see is is that רב Rav is
willing to go by אומדנא. umdana. So therefore if רב Rav goes
by אומדנא umdana? in this case of this gift of a שכיב
מרע and if רבי נתן Rabbi Natan goes by אומדנא umdana in
the case of the guy who says write a גט for my
wife, so then how do we know which what's their debate by
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah about the תוספת? tosefet
Okay, people with me? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
says the תוספת tosefet was written in the כתובה ketubah from the
time of אירוסין erusin but it doesn't really kick in until the
time of נישואין. And that's because we go by what we think
the guy is thinking even though he didn't say it even though
it's not written. But we see both רב Rav and רבי נתן
Rabbi Natan are willing to go by what the guy must be
thinking if it's not explicit. So how do we know what's their
debate about whether we go like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah or not? But the גמרא Gemara is inserting that into
the משנה, Mishnah. right? We don't know that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was based on אומדנא umdana. issue. Well right
but but well I don't know I mean רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says שלא כתב לה shelo katav la I
mean he is the language of the שטר shtar only says one
thing and רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says what's
he say? He says check back in the משנה. Mishnah Yeah but
his reason is מנהגא דכולהו מקדמי שלא כתב לה אלא על מנת
לכונסה. minhagaz kol mekatmen shelo katav la ela al m'nat lachonsah. Who
told you? That's not written. He is saying I know that the
guy only wrote it with this in mind, right? So I mean
the גמרא Gemara is phrasing it as אומדנא. umdana Right, meaning that's
the right that's the funny thing right meaning that's the funny thing
is that the גמרא Gemara makes it a debate about whether you
go by אומדנא umdana? whereas you could say everybody's prepared to go
by אומדנא, umdana we always just debate what the אומדנא umdana is,
right? So the גמרא Gemara. does make it as if there's a
question but that's what's going to turn to because now we've exactly
we're getting there because רב Rav, and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan we
see in other places go by אומדנא. umdana So their debate here
must be what is the אומדנא? umdana, So that's exactly the next
stage of the גמרא. Gemara אלא Ella so that's exactly what we
say now here top of נ"ו. nun vav. אלא תרוייהו אזלי בתר
אומדנא. Ella tarvayhu azli batar umdana. Fine we see they go by
אומדנא umdana, but that doesn't just because you're willing to sometimes try
to figure out context, you could debate what that context is. מ"ד
הלכה Man d'amar halacha the one that says we rule like רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya שפיר shapir that makes sense.
We say even though the שטר says now we'll assume it meant
later and because we go by אומדנא. umdana, מ"ד אין הלכה Man
d'amar ein halacha we don't rule like him הכא נמי אמדינן דעתיה.
hacha nami amdinan datahu. Okay, we go by אומדנא umdena, but what
is the אומדנא? What do we assume he meant? משום אקרובי דעתא
הוא mishum ikruvay datahu we assume he wrote the תוספת tosefet not
just because for the anticipation of actually having the נישואין and when
they actually were you know together and would have sex and so
on and that was then when he wanted to give it. No,
he wanted to give her the תוספת tosefes, now because they're feeling
so you know close to one another because they're already at the
time of אירוסין. erusin. והא איקרב ליה דעתיה v'ha ikrav la data
and therefore already now he's feeling close to her. So fine we
go by אומדנא but אומדנא doesn't necessarily mean that your assessment of
his דעת daat. that I agree with your assessment of his דעת.
daat We could both agree that we try to assess his דעת
daas. but it doesn't mean that I necessarily agree with what that
is. Now I want to say something about this אזלינן בתר אומדנא
azlinan batar umdana because this raises a serious questions about the general
principle that's in the opposite of אזלינן בתר אומדנא azlinan basar umdana,
which is דברים שבלב אינם דברים dvarim shebalev einam dvarim that we
don't care what you're thinking we care what you said and what
you wrote. So in all these cases right, if he wrote, if
he said כתבו גט לאשתי, kisvu get l'ishti, he just said כתבו,
kisvu, if he said I'm giving you, he wrote the amount in
the כתובה kesuvah now, if he wrote it now, why should we
assume later? So here רמב״ם Rambam and תוספות רי״ד Tosafos Rid both
say the same thing except in different ways, and they say that
the basic difference is that דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim she-be-lev einam
devarim applies to two-sided transactions. If I sell you something, then you're
giving money, I'm selling you something, I can't say oh here's what
I really meant, here's what I was thinking. Now, if it's like
blatant the context, okay, that's called דברים שבלב כל אדם, devarim she-be-lev
kol adam, like it's obvious to everybody that when I said X
this is what I meant, this was the context and so on.
But if it's not self-evident then it doesn't matter what I was
thinking, you're on the other side of the equation, you don't have
any responsibility to guess what I was thinking and the transaction is
defined by what's explicit. When we say אזלינן בתר אומדנא, that's by
one-sided transactions and all the three cases we just looked at here
are one-sided transactions. What were they? גט, the woman doesn't have a
say, so it's all what the husband wants, מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas
sh'chiv mera a gift, one-sided, and תוספת, tosefes because even though there
are reciprocal aspects of the כתובה, kesuvah, the תוספת כתובה tosefes kesuvah
is all one-sided, right, the בעל baal is just deciding what to
give, there's no explicit exchange about that. Now it might be he's
willing to give a תוספת tosefes because she's giving a bigger dowry
and so on, but that's not explicitly framed as such and therefore
we're prepared to go by אומדנא and not say דברים שבלב אינם
דברים. devarim she-be-lev einam devarim. Even when we say that though, we
have to figure out what are you really thinking. And that's what
the debate is. I should say by the way that all that
being said, the case about מתנת שכיב מרע שכתוב בה קנין matnas
sh'chiv mera she-kasuv bah kinyan is hard to understand why the גמרא
Gemara. frames it as an אומדנא, because you basically have a document
that's self-contradictory. Half the document is being framed as a מתנת שכיב
מרע and has components of it which are like a normal well-person
gift. So you have to forget אומדנא, there's like contradictory phrasings within
the document itself and you have to figure out how to reconcile
it, how to interpret it. That's very different when the actual thing
in front of you is black and white and you're going to
insert something based on your assumption of what the guy is thinking.
Okay, but anyway that's what we have in the גמרא. Gemara So
now let's take a look. So now we understand that רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya. is based on אומדנא, and our
assumption that he only wanted this to kick in at the time
of the נשואין. nisuin. And now we have to figure out do
we פוסקן pasken like that or not. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: יתיב רב חנינא קמיה דרבי ינאי, yasiv Rav Chanina kamei
de-Rebbi Yannai, רב חנינא Rav Chanina was sitting in front of רבי
ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, וקאמר הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, v'ka'amar halacha k'Rebbi
Elazar ben Azarya, we rule like him. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
רבי ינאי Rebbi Yannai said to him, פוק קרי קראך לברא גורי,
puk kari kerach l'bara gori, your פסוק pasuk outside. אין הלכה כרבי
אלעזר בן עזריה. ein halacha k'Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya. We don't rule
like him. אמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי משום רבינו. amar Rebbi Yitzchak
bar Avdimi mishum Rabbeinu. Yeah, that's a saying like yeah, exactly. Go
fly a kite. אמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי משום רבינו, amar Rebbi
Yitzchak bar Avdimi mishum Rabbeinu, so רבי יצחק בר אבדימי Rebbi Yitzchak
bar Avdimi said in the name of רבינו, Rabbeinu, which is רב,
הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, halacha k'Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya, we rule
like him. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה,
amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya, שמואל Shmuel
says we rule like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya
ורב נחמן דידיה אמר, v'Rav Nachman didei amar, רב נחמן Rav Nachman
himself says, אין הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, ein halacha k'Rebbi Elazar
ben Azarya, we don't rule like him. ובנהרדעי משמיה דרב נחמן אמרי,
uv'Nahardai mishmei de-Rav Nachman amri, but בנהרדעי Nahardai in the name of
רב נחמן Rav Nachman say, הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, halacha k'Rebbi
Elazar ben Azarya, we rule like him. ואף על גב דלט רב
נחמן, v'af al gav d'lot Rav Nachman, even though רב נחמן Rav
Nachman cursed, דאמר and said, כל דיינא דדאין כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה,
kol dayana d'dayen k'Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya, any judge that rules like
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya. and does not award
the תוספת tosefes from the time of the אירוסין, eirusin, הכי והכי
תהוי, hachi v'hachi tehavei, such and such should befall him. גמרא Gemara
didn't spell out what the curse was. אפילו הכי הלכה כרבי אלעזר
בן עזריה, afilu hachi halacha k'Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya, we rule like
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rebbi Elazar ben Azarya. We overrule רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. והלכה למעשה, v'halacha l'maaseh, and bottom line if it was
not clear, we rule in practice like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rebbi
Elazar ben Azarya והלכה למעשה, v'halacha l'maaseh, sometimes the גמרא Gemara, does
say that, right, והלכה למעשה, v'halacha l'maaseh, you know, but it is
funny הלכה halacha, after right after everything saying הלכה, halacha הלכה למעשה,
halacha l'maaseh, which just means like in practice we actually do rule
like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah and the כתובה
kesuvah obligations, the תוספת tosefes, does not kick in until the נשואין.
nisuin. Since we're talking about interesting phrases of והלכה למעשה, v'halacha l'maaseh,
I needed to mention that yesterday, two days ago, I'm losing track,
anyway, you have the phrase לכאורה, lichora, right, I think it was
like it might have been the only time the word לכאורה lichora
appears in the גמרא, Gemara I have to check, but if not
the only, one of the only times, so what does that word
mean? So there's actually interesting, right? The גמרא Gemara, says לכאורה lichora
it looks like this opinion but when you go more deeper you
see it's not connected to this opinion. So the ערוך Aruch says
לכאורה lichora means לכאורה l'k'ora which means like towards first light, meaning
at first glance it looks like this, okay, the first light it
looks like this. The תוספות רי״ד Tosafos Rid גרסא girsa was לכיעורה
l'chiora with an עין. ayin. And he said it means like ugly,
a poor way of looking at it, you'd come with this assessment.
Like if you're not real, you know, but... If you have a
better way of looking at it, or then you'll come to a
better understanding of what it's about. What I think is interesting about
that הלכה למעשה halacha lemaaseh is it's Hebrew, it's not Aramaic instead
of להלכתא. lehilchata. That's true, in Hebrew, so it's as if it's
the Hebrew translation of הילכתא hilchata A, and B why is it
in Hebrew? Why is it in Hebrew? Yeah, that's an interesting question.
I don't know. He also said הלכה halacha? right before it said
הלכה למעשה halacha lemaaseh also. So I don't know. Okay, בעי רבא.
baei Rava. Now Rava asked: נכנסה לחופה, nichnesa lechupa, now that we're
ruling like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah. and it
goes by נשואין nisuin when the woman is entitled to the תוספת,
tosefes, we want to define what exactly is that moment of נשואין?
nisuin? So, because you know, I mean we normally know when נשואין
nisuin is for all the normal כתובה kesubah obligations, but this is
a question about his דעת. He wrote already wrote the תוספת, tosefes
right? So it's not a question like when is he entitled to
מזונות, mezonos, when is she entitled to מזונות? mezonos? That we know,
that's חופה. chupa. Okay, but here, right, the normal כתובה kesubah obligations
are real נשואין. nisuin. But this is he already wrote the תוספת
tosefes? in the document and we just said he wanted to wait
until they actually were together. So does that technically mean חופה chupa
or could it be a different time? So let's take a look.
So בעי רבא: baei Rava: נכנסה לחופה ולא נבעלה. nichnesa lechupa velo
niv'ala. They had the חופה chupa but they haven't had sex. מהו?
mahu? What's the הלכה? halachah חיבת חופה קונה? chibas chupa koneh? The
sort of, you know, the closeness, the intimacy of the חופה chupa
is enough for to be קונה, koneh, I don't think romance was
an idea in the גמרא, Gemara but okay, the intimacy of the
חופה chupa was enough of the idea for was enough closeness for
her to now be entitled to the תוספת? tosefes, או חיבת ביאה
קונה, o chibas bia koneh, or does it have to be the
actual time of sex? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דתני
רב יוסף, detani Rav Yosef, שלא כתב לה אלא על חיבת לילה
הראשון. shelo chasav lah ela al chibas laila harishon. Rav Yosef said
to explain רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, he wrote it only for the
because of the intimacy of the first night. אי אמרת בשלמא חיבת
חופה קונה, ei amart bishlama chibas chupa koneh, if you say we're
talking about the חופה chupa without the sex, see I would've thought
לילה הראשון laila harishon means sex, let's see what the גמרא Gemara.
says, if you were to said that we're talking about the חופה,
chupa, היינו דאמר לילה הראשון. hainu de'amar laila harishon. That's why he
emphasized the first night because חופה chupa only occurs once. אלא אי
אמרת חיבת ביאה קונה, ela ei amart chibas bia koneh, if he
meant sex, ביאת לילה הראשון איתא מכאן ואילך ליתא? biat laila harishon
issa mikan ve'eilach leissa? What, there's only sex on the first night,
not afterwards? I understand it meant that that's when it kicks in,
but okay. ואלא מאי חופה, ve'ela mai chupa, says the גמרא. Gemara
So what do you think חופה chupa means? אלא מאי, ela mai,
what do you think? חופה? chupa? חופה בלילה איתא ביממא ליתא? chupa
belaila issa beyimama leissa? So why did he say the first night?
What, you think חופה chupa you can only have at night, you
can't have in the day? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, ולטעמיך,
uletamaich, back to you, ביאה בלילה איתא ביממא ליתא? bia belaila issa
beyimama leissa? If he meant sex, why would he also have said
night? You think you can only have sex at night, not in
the day? הא אמר רבא, ha amar Rava, doesn't Rava say, אם
היה בבית אפל, im haya bevayis afel, although normally the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, that the it sort of discourages sex during the
day, it says that if it's a dark house, מותר, mutar, it's
permissible. So it's not that sex is only at night. He says,
no, הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's not difficult. Even if
that's true that sex could be at the day, אורח ארעא קא
משמע לן. orach ar'a ka mashma lan. It's the normal way דביאה
בלילה, debia belaila, that sex is at night. So if he wants
to talk about sex, he's going to talk about night. אלא חופה
קשיא, ela chupa kashya, but if it was really the חופה chupa
that did it, it wouldn't have said night. He says, no, חופה
נמי לא קשיא. chupa nami lo kashya. חופה chupa also it's not
difficult why it said night. כיון דסתם חופה לביאה קיימא, keivan destam
chupa lebia ka'ima, since חופה chupa is a lead-in to them being,
you know, physically together and having sex, אורח ארעא קא משמע לן,
orach ar'a ka mashma lan, so therefore, לביאה קיימא אורח ארעא קא
משמע לן דבלילה, lebia ka'ima orach ar'a ka mashma lan debalaila, that
it's going to be at night, or either to indicate חופה chupa
is because it's a lead-in to sex which will be at night,
or maybe in general חופה chupa should be at night. Anyway, so
this phrase of the first night is not clear whether he means
that he's writing it because of anticipating the חופה chupa or anticipating
the sex. Okay, so we don't know the answer. בעי רב אשי:
baei Rav Ashi: so Rav Ashi asked: נכנסה לחופה ופירסה נדה מהו?
nichnesa lechupa ufirsa nida mahu? Let's say there was a חופה chupa
and then she became a נדה. nida. אם תימצי לומר חיבת חופה
קונה, im timtzi lomar chibas chupa koneh, if you say that just
חופה chupa itself is enough for her to be entitled to the
תוספת, tosefes? so חופה דחזיא לביאה, chupa dechazya lebia, maybe that's only
a חופה chupa where it was a lead-in to sex, אבל חופה
דלא חזיא לביאה, aval chupa delo chazya lebia, if it was not
a lead-in to sex, לא, it's not, או דילמא לא שנא, o
dilma lo shena, maybe it doesn't matter? תיקו. teiku. Now we don't
know. Now the funny thing here is that what do you mean
whether it's חזיא לביאה chazya lebia or not? Because the נפקא מינה
nafka mina of these cases is, what's the נפקא מינה nafka mina
of these cases? They had חופה chupa and he dropped dead before
they had sex. That would be the נפקא מינה nafka mina of
the first case. Is she entitled to the תוספת? tosefes. So that
was also, no, no, no, we're talking about תוספת. tosefes? This is
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah So the 100 and
200 she gets from the time of אירוסין. eirusin. Okay, so he
they had חופה chupa and he dropped dead, does she get the
תוספת? tosefes. So that wasn't, it was חזיא לביאה chazya lebia at
the time, but it wasn't חזיא לביאה chazya lebia retroactively because he
dropped dead, right? Why what's everybody so confused about? The משנה Mishna
is clear. She gets 100 and 200 from the time of the
אירוסין. eirusin. The debate is that you wrote a תוספת. tosefes? When
does she get the תוספת? tosefes. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah says only from the time of נשואין. nisuin. Is this
clear to people? It wasn't obvious to me, to tell you the
truth, I wasn't certain that he was. It's only about the תוספת.
tosefes It says נתאלמנה או נתגרשה בין מן האירוסין בין מן הנשואין.
nisalmena o nisgarsha bein min haeirusin bein min hanisuin. Right? So from
the אירוסין, erusin, so from... fine, but that... no, that we say
is from the time of אירוסין. erusin. That רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, says, that basic obligation, that might be there
even if you wrote nothing. That's part of the rabbinic obligation, and
I based... So he drops dead after the חופה chuppah before they've
had sex. Okay, so the תנא קמא says whatever, תנא קמא says
he could drop dead a minute after the אירוסין erusin after writing
the כתובה kesubah and she gets it all. But here, for רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah she's only going to get
the תוספת tosefes? after נישואין. So there was a חופה chuppah and
he drops dead. Does she get the תוספת? tosefes, So that was
the first question. Okay, now, and we... so we don't know whether
it's from the time of חופה chuppah or the time of sex.
So now the גמרא Gemara, says assuming it's from the time of
חופה, chuppah, and if he drops dead right afterwards she's going to
get the תוספת, tosefes. what if she becomes a נדה? niddah? Okay,
because then it was a חופה chuppah that wasn't ראוי לביאה. ra'uy
leviah. But the question is why does becoming a נדה niddah right
after the חופה chuppah any different than dropping dead right after the
חופה? chuppah? At the time of the חופה, chuppah, presumably she wasn't
a נדה, niddah, right? So at the time of the חופה chuppah
he wasn't dead, she wasn't a נדה, niddah, at that time everything
was okay, so then she should... if she should be entitled to
it. So whether a minute later he drops dead or a minute
later she becomes a נדה niddah and then he drops dead, either
way she should get the תוספת. tosefes So it sounds like she
was a נדה niddah at the time of the חופה, chuppah, not
afterwards. And then you understand the question. One scenario is a חופה,
chuppah, he drops dead, so she already was entitled to it by
the time of the חופה, chuppah, but what if she was a
נדה niddah at the time of the חופה? chuppah? Then that חופה
chuppah was not a חופה chuppah that was ראוי לביאה, ra'uy leviah,
and that's the issue. Okay, so when it says נכנסה לחופה ופירסה
נדה, nichnesah lechuppah upirsah niddah, פירסה נדה, pirsah niddah, the logical way
of understanding this question is she had already been a נדה niddah
at the time of the חופה. chuppah. Is this... am I being
clear here or not? Okay, so you're suggesting she'd been dead at
the time of the חופה? chuppah? That is thing... that's clear. The
reason I'm making a point about this is because it's a major
מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim whether חופת נדה chuppas niddah counts as a
חופה chuppah or not. And this גמרא, Gemara you could read it
two ways: there was חופה chuppah and then she became a נדה,
niddah, but that would be bizarre, once there was חופה chuppah and
once we say חופה chuppah works, what matters... why does it matter
she
became a נדה niddah afterwards? The same way if he dropped dead
afterwards, she already
was entitled to it from the time of the חופה. chuppah. So
if it means she was already a נדה, niddah, then it would
indicate that חופת נדה chuppas
niddah in general... you
know I would think it would indicate חופת נדה chuppas niddah in
general would count, but the only question here is does it count
for this issue of the תוספת tosefes, or not. Yes, yeah, so
exactly as we might say, that's what the ראשונים Rishonim argue about.
So it could be, yeah, that's... I mean that's why this גמרא
Gemara is exactly vague along that point. Does this גמרא Gemara mean
she became a נדה niddah afterwards, and then we're free to discuss
what it mean... what it would be if she was a נדה
niddah at the time of the חופה? chuppah? Or does it mean
she was a נדה niddah at the time of the חופה chuppah
and maybe what we're discussing is not just the תוספת, tosefes but
maybe what we're discussing is whether חופת נדה chuppas niddah in general
counts as a חופה chuppah or not. Right. But this is... the
גמרא Gemara says within that position, why? Because as we discussed earlier
by חופה, chuppah, חופה chuppah symbolizes two things: it's the house of
the בעל ba'al and it's that sense of of ביאה. bi'ah. So
if ביאה bi'ah is not possible at the time of חופה, chuppah,
maybe חופה chuppah doesn't mean חופה. chuppah. Even though he's taking her...
he's going into this presumably for the long haul. It doesn't matter.
So what? Though you haven't yet done that act that signifies the
next stage of the marriage. Yeah, so I want to know like
what do they mean by חופה? chuppah? חופה chuppah is like what
we're thinking like... So the גמרא Gemara it's never black... yeah, so
there's a major מחלוקת ראשונים. machlokes Rishonim. It's never black and white.
It was obviously some event that occurred before they act... before ביאה.
bi'ah. So it sounds like, you know, there what would we do
with the whole poles and whatever? I mean, there's a whole מחלוקת
ראשונים machlokes Rishonim what it is. It was something like that if
not exactly what we're doing right now. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says תיקו. teiku. So the point... bottom line is is that
this גמרא Gemara is discussing when the תוספת tosefes. kicks in according
to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה and it's question whether is it חופה
chuppah or is it ביאה. bi'ah. If it's חופה, chuppah, what if
it's a חופה chuppah that's not ראוי לביאה? ra'uy leviah? What if
it's a חופה chuppah that's a נדה? niddah? And that is connected
to a discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim in general whether חופת נדה
chuppas niddah counts as חופה chuppah for anything, but in our case
we're talking specifically about the תוספת. Yes. I'm just wondering about אומדנא,
you know, to work the other way around. Like you know, if
the father-in-law who's giving this big dowry and then she dies under
the חופה, chuppah, you know, you don't say that he gets it
back because, like
you know, he only wanted it because they wanted it...
Yeah, well, there there
clearly the dowry only transfers at the time of the נישואין.
Okay, for that, you know, so... But does חופת נדה, chuppas niddah,
I mean, take effect either with the dowry, right? Well, the only
reason that he would get the dowry is because of the הלכה
halacha that a husband inherits his wife and that's the חז"ל, Chazal,
that's not up to the father. חז"ל *Chazal* established that the husband
inherits his wife only from the time of ניסואין *nissu'in* whereas here
he's writing a debt and he's writing a debt that's you know
so there it's you know it is based on what he's obligating
himself, not just the structure that חז"ל *Chazal* have created. Okay, Rabbi
Yehuda אומר omer, *omer*, so that's the issue about the תוספת *tosefet*.
Now we're going back to Rabbi Yehuda we saw before that you,
as long as you write the base of 200 or 100, she
can write a receipt in order to lower the amount. Rabbi Yehuda
אומר *omer*, רוצה כותב לבתולה *rotzeh kotev l'betulah* if you want to
write to a בתולה *betulah* write 200 or אלמנה *almanah* 100 and
she can write a receipt that she's been paid half or paid
however much, even if she hasn't really been paid that. Of the
תוספת *tosefet* again? No, עיקר *ikar* base, עיקר *ikar* base. Rabbi Yehuda
allows the base to be lower than the minimum as long as
in the כתובה kesubah *ketubah* you wrote the basic minimum, then she
can effectively make it less by writing him a שובר *shover*. It's
a מחילה *mechila*. Right. וסבר רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda. דכותבין שובר *V'savar
Rabbi Yehuda de'kotvin shover*? Now does Rabbi Yehuda really hold that you
can write a receipt? והתנן *Ve'hatnan*, we have taught in the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah*, מי שפרע מקצת חובו *mi she'para miktzat chovo*, I owed
Dov ten thousand dollars and I paid three thousand of it. רבי
יהודה אומר Reb Yehuda Omer: יחליף *Rabbi Yehuda omer yachlif*. So Rabbi
Yehuda says, so now what are we going to do? Because I
want to so because I don't want Dov to come back to
me with the ten thousand dollar שטר *shtar*. So Rabbi Yehuda says,
fine, tear up the old שטר *shtar* and write seven thousand now.
רבי יוסי אומר יכתוב לו שובר *Rabbi Yossi omer yichtov lo shover*.
He has to give him a new שטר *shtar*? Yeah, write him
a new שטר *shtar*. Rabbi Yossi says, no, Dov here writes me
a receipt for three thousand and then next time he comes with
the שטר *shtar* for ten thousand I'll produce the receipt for three
thousand. So what's the difference? The difference is that if we write
a receipt it puts on me a burden to save my receipts,
which makes sense. I'm the guy that owes him the money, I
should have the responsibility. Okay, that's יכתוב שובר *yichtov shover*. But the
other opinion, Rabbi Yehuda says, I don't, that's not fair to put
on the לוה loveh, *loveh* the burden to save the receipts. And
therefore we're going to tear up the old ten thousand and make
it seven thousand. Now, what's not fair about doing that? What's not
fair about doing that? He's writing a new שטר *shtar*. Well, okay,
besides the expense, it's also expensive writing a receipt. No, the bigger
נפקא מינה *nafka mina* is that now Dov's liens that he had
on my property from five years ago when I borrowed it, if
we write a new שטר *shtar today for seven thousand, he loses
those five years of liens. He only has liens starting today. So
the receipt idea makes a lot more sense.
Nevertheless, Rabbi Yehuda
is
so much protecting the לוה loveh *loveh* there that he doesn't allow
he says we're not going to write receipts even if it's going
to mean a loss of liens. So how here can Rabbi Yehuda
say that I can the woman should write a receipt to the
husband? He doesn't, he normally doesn't allow for receipts. Did she actually
receive money or just, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to say. That's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
say. You know, you don't have to protect the husband here because
he didn't actually pay out any money. That's exactly the גמרא's Gemara
*Gemara's* answer. So let's take a look. אמר רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiya,
*Amar Rabbi Yirmiya*, so well we'll give your answer in a minute
but first let's put another one. אמר רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiya כשהשוברה
טבועה מתוכה *Amar Rabbi Yirmiya k'she'shovra tevua mitocha*. You're right, in this
case it's not a receipt that's handed to the בעל *ba'al*. In
the כתובה kesubah, *ketubah* itself it says it was a debt of
200 of which 100 has already been paid. Okay, so in the
כתובה Kesuvah *ketubah* itself so therefore the husband doesn't have to hold
on to a receipt because the lowering of the amount, the receipt,
is effectively already in the כתובה Kesuvah. *ketubah*. אביי Abaye אמר אפילו
תימא בשאין שוברה טבועה מתוכה *Abaye amar afilu teima b'she'ein shovra tevua
mitocha*, even if there's no receipt written into the כתובה Kesuvah *ketubah*.
בשלמא התם ודאי פרע *Bishlama hatam vaday para*, in the case where
I paid my three thousand dollars I paid out real money. דילמא
מירכס תברתא *Dilma mirchas tavrata*, maybe so there Rabbi Yehuda's concerned I'll
lose, the word מירכס *mirchas* means I'll lose my receipt, שוברא *shovra*,
right because it breaks, it breaks the obligation, that's why the receipt
is called a שובר *shover*. So I really paid my three thousand
dollars, we're afraid I'm going to lose my receipt. ומפיק ליה לשטרא
*U'mapik leh l'shtra* and Dov will take out the ten thousand dollar
document וגבי ביה זימנא אחרינא *ve'gabi bei zimna achrina* and he'll use
it to collect that three thousand dollars of the debt a second
time. So we want to protect me because I really paid real
money. הכא *Hacha*, in this case, ודאי יהב לה *vaday yahav lah*,
did he give her any money? No. מילתא בעלמא הוא דאמרה ליה
*Milta b'alma hu d'amra leh*. She's just saying he gave me the
money but he didn't really. It was just a way of lowering
the debt. So if we're doing this nice thing to the husband
that we're lowering the debt even though he didn't pay any money,
it's his responsibility to watch the receipt.
אי נטר נטר *Ei natar natar*, if he watches the receipt, good.
אי לא נטר איהו דאפסיד אנפשיה *Ei lo natar ihu d'afsid anafshei*,
he you know he brought it upon himself. We have no רחמנות
*rachmanut* for the husband. He got a lowering of a debt without
paying any money. Even here Rabbi Yehuda is not afraid is not
concerned about writing a receipt.
What didn't he go, what didn't he keep? The receipt. In the
כתובה Kesuvah *ketubah* itself? No, the receipt. No, no, no, that was
the first answer, was it in the. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like: בשלמא אביי לא אמר כרבי ירמיה. Bishlama Abaye lo amar
k'Rebbe Yirmiya. אביי Abaye? didn't say like רבי ירמיה, לא תני שפטר
תלמיד חכם. lo tani shepitar talmid chacham. The משנה didn't say that
you have to write it in the כתובה Kesuvah? itself, and that
would very much limit the position of רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda אל
רבי ירמיה מאי טעמא לא אמר כאביי? El Rebbe Yirmiya mai taama
lo amar k'Abaye? Why didn't רבי ירמיה say like אביי? Makes an
enormous amount of sense. Even רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda who doesn't want
to protect the לוה, why, here, go ahead and write a receipt,
the husband didn't put out any money. So he says, in principle
you're right, but גזירה שובר דהכא אטו שובר דעלמא. gezeira shovar de'hacha
atu shovar de'alma. He assumes that since רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is
against the receipt, he wouldn't allow receipt even here. If you allow
receipt here, people will come to write receipts and assume that you
can force the לוה to hold on to the receipt in other
cases as well. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this: טעמא
דכתב ליה, Taama de'chasav lei, the reason you can lower the amount
according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, is because he literally writes out,
because he actually writes out the receipt. אבל על פה לא. Aval
al peh, lo. But if she would just verbally say, if they
would agree let's make the amount less than 200, let's make the
amount 100, presumably that wouldn't work, right? Because you have to have
the debt, have the base amount and then lower it. You can't
start with a lower amount. אמאי? Amai? Why not? דבר שבממון הוא,
Davar she'bemamon hu, this is a monetary debt. ושמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה,
Veshaminan lei l'Rebbe Yehuda, and we know according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda he says דבר שבממון תנאו קיים, davar she'bemamon tnao kayam, that
a person can stipulate against monetary obligations, even biblical monetary obligations. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Braisa: האומר לאשה, Ha'omer le'isha, a
man says to a woman, הרי את מקודשת לי על מנת שאין
לי עליך שאר כסות ועונה. harei at mekudeshes li al mnat she'ein
li alayich she'eir ksut ve'ona. I am, you are married to me
on the condition that you don't have on me any right, I
don't have any obligation to you, for מזונות, mzonos, for food, for
clothes and for sex. הרי זו מקודשת ותנאו בטל דברי רבי מאיר.
Harei zu mekudeshes utnao batel, divrei Rebbe Meir. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
says, so the קידושין kiddushin works, the stipulation is void because it's
מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה, matneh al mah shekatuv ba'Torah, you're trying
to stipulate against תורה Torah obligations. Those stipulations are void and the
קידושין kiddushin still takes effect. וכל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו
בטל. ve'at matneh al mah shekatuv ba'Torah tnao batel. That's רבי מאיר.
Rebbe Meir. רבי יהודה אומר בדבר שבממון תנאו קיים, Rebbe Yehuda omer,
bedavar she'bemamon tnao kayam, a famous debate, that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
says you can stipulate even against a תורה Torah obligation in a
monetary realm. The way רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda presumably understands it is,
is that when the תורה Torah says, like for example, let's take
an easier case. א שומר חנם A shomer chinam is חייב בפשיעה.
chayav be'pshia. I ask somebody to watch something, I don't pay him
for it, he's חייב chayav in negligence. I pay him for it,
he's חייב chayav in a higher degree. So you could say the
תורה Torah absolutely mandates that that's what א שומר חנם a shomer
chinam has to pay and you can't stipulate it against it, or
you can say no, bottom line is, how much is Michael going
to have to pay me if he watches my object is basically
a transaction between two people and we could really stipulate anything. It's
just the תורה Torah just tells me what the default assumptions are.
But that's the default. If I wanted to stipulate otherwise and it's
between the two of us, why shouldn't it? It's just a monetary
debt. So no, so what רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is saying is
עונה ona you can't stipulate against, but שאר וכסות, she'eir veksut, if
the תורה Torah says those are your obligations, תורה Torah doesn't say
a husband must pay his wife שאר וכסות. she'eir veksut. Says we
are going to assume as a matter of default that a marriage
will normally be with an implicit stipulation of שאר וכסות. she'eir veksut.
If you want to go ahead and frame it otherwise in monetary
realms, well, why not? It's a monetary obligation, you are free to
stipulate whatever monetary realm you... Except עונה ona is not, עונה's ona
not monetary, that your תנאי tnai would be בטל, batel, but שאר
וכסות she'eir veksut it's קיים. kayam. So if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
holds that you're always free to reframe the monetary obligations in the
תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah is just sort of telling you what
the default assumption is, then why can't you reframe the 200 or
the 100 of the כתובה, Kesuvah. which is anyway probably only דרבנן
d'rabbanan if anything? If you could do it for biblical stuff, why
not for דרבנן? d'rabbanan? At this point you could also say that
עונה ona is something that usually we, if you have a personal
obligation... Right, so maybe even a personal obligation between people. Right. Meaning
still עונה's ona different than let's say the... right. So you could
say עונה's ona still different than like איסורין. issurin. It's still about
a relationship of people and maybe that could be shaped as well.
That's true. In theory you might have been able to extend it
there, but that's where he doesn't go. So the גמרא says like
this, maybe because ממון mamon you can always just give money over
whereas personal obligations... What? You can't. Yeah. So it's not necessarily עונה
ona so much... Right. Okay. No, you're right. Okay, okay, okay. It
is a good point, but by money you have more latitude in
general, like you can create monetary obligations on yourself, but anyway, but
yes, in theory you could have said it there. He doesn't go
that far. But now let's ask, if רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda gives
you all this latitude by monetary obligations, why can't you directly just
say less than 200? Why do you have to do this, why
do you have to do it as a two-step process? Just stipulate
it's less than 200. So the גמרא says קסבר רבי יהודה כתובה
דרבנן, Kasavar Rebbe Yehuda kesuvah d'rabbanan, so here's the counter-intuitive answer. Yes.
That's what he holds by biblical obligations. But רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda
holds כתובה's Kesuvah Rabbinic. וחכמים עשו חיזקו לדבריהם יותר משל תורה. VeChachamim
Assu Chizku LeDivreihem Yoter Mishel Torah. Right? But the Rabbis were more
stringent by כתובה. Biblical obligations didn't need greater strengthening, Rabbinic obligations כתובה
we did not want people to treat leniently, or you might want
to say we wanted to really make sure that the woman was
protected, although שאר כסות she'er kesus is also protection. And therefore he
did not let a direct lowering of the כתובה amount. Let's just
read, let's just turn the page or go one more minute. The
גמרא says like this. הרי פירות דרבנן, Harei Peiros DeRabbanan, one minute,
the fact that the husband can eat the פירות, peiros, the fruit
of the wife's נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, the property the wife brings
in that she retains title to into the marriage and the husband
gets the, you know, the money that it earns, the פירות. peiros.
So that's Rabbinic, ולא עבדו להו רבנן חיזוק, velo avdu lehu Rabbanan
chizuk, and the Rabbis didn't strengthen, didn't prevent the husband, the wife
from stipulating against it. How do you know? דתנן, DeTnan, we taught
in a משנה. רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda אומר: לעולם הוא אוכל פירות
פירות, LeOlam hu ochel perei peiros, עד שיכתוב לה. ad sheyichtov lah.
That let's say the husband says to the wife and he says
I don't have any rights into the fruit of your property. So
the הלכה is he doesn't have ownership of the fruits, but he
owns the fruit of the fruits. What does that mean? Like you
know when you reinvest the dividends, so you know you reinvest the
dividends and you bought more stock and those dividends are now earning
dividends. So even if he waives the rights to the fruit, he
doesn't waive the rights to the fruit of the fruit unless he
says that explicitly. So that's what רבי יהודה says. לעולם הוא אוכל
פירות פירות, LeOlam hu ochel perei peiros, even if he waives the
rights to the fruit, he doesn't waive the rights to the fruit
of the fruit, עד שיכתוב לה ad sheyichtov lah unless he writes
explicitly: דין ודברים אין לי בנכסייך, Din udevarim ein li banichsayich, any
like judgment, any case claim I give up, אין לי, ein li,
I give up any claim בנכסייך banichsayich against your property, ובפירותיהן ubepeiroteihen
and their fruit, ובפירות פירותיהן ubepeirei peiroteihen and the fruit of their
fruit, עד עולם ad olam ad infinitum. Okay? So that's just saying
about when does he stipulate against any rights? He has to be
explicit that he's giving up all the rights to the fruit and
the fruit of the fruit etc. Now why that's relevant for us
is the next line. וקיימא לן VeKayma Lan and we have established
in that סוגיא sugya over there, מאי כותב mai kosev when it
says he writes to waive those rights, it doesn't literally mean write.
What does it mean that he writes? It means אומר, that as
long as he can verbally waive the rights. So look, if he's
entitled to the פירות, peiros, that's Rabbinic, and רבי יהודה says that
he's allowed to waive the rights to the פירות peiros even verbally.
So why can he waive the rights to the פירות peiros and
not waive the rights to the basic amount of the כתובה? So
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so everybody get the question? If we're going
to protect Rabbinic institutions, then why don't we protect it by the
fruits? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לכל יש כתובה ולא לכל יש
פירות. lekol yesh Kesuvah velo lekol yesh peiros. Everybody gets a כתובה.
Not everybody brings in property and has פירות. peiros. So if they're
going to protect, they're going to protect the כתובה which every woman
is entitled to. They're not necessarily going to protect the פירות peiros
which is a rarer situation. מילתא דשכיחא עבדו רבנן חיזוק, Milsa deshchicha
avdu Rabbanan chizuk, something that was common, every single woman is entitled
to the 200 and the 100, they're going to protect that. מילתא
דלא שכיחא, Milsa delo shchicha, something less common that if somebody brings
in property that they retain title to, לא עבדו רבנן חיזוק, lo
avdu רבנן חיזוק, they are not going to act as a way
to protect it. They're not going to do something special to protect
that. So we're going to finish up this tomorrow about this issue
about when can you make stipulations against Rabbinic or against biblical obligations.
So he still can't get out of his obligation to her. He
says I'm not going to eat the פירות peiros and in return
I'm not going to give.